And now the time has come to curate our data set.
이제 데이터 세트를 큐레이팅할 때가 됐어요
And the way we're going to do this is we're going to take each of the data points that we got from hugging
어떻게 할 거냐면요 얼굴을 안아서 얻은 각각의 데이터 포인트를 가지고
face, and we're going to convert it into a Python object, an object, a class that we're going to
파이썬 객체로 변환할 겁니다 우리가 생성할 클래스로 항목이라고 부르는
create called an item.
객체죠
And it's so important that I've actually set up a different module items.py, where I have written this
다른 모듈 항목을 셋업하는 건 정말 중요해요 파이썬 코드를 이용해서 이 클래스를 만들었습니다
class, and I've done it as Python code, not in a Jupyter notebook, but in its own own module, so
주피터 노트북이 아니라 파이썬 코드 모듈에서 다루었습니다 여러 곳에서 다시 사용할 수 있습니다
that it can be reused from different places, and so that we don't clutter our Jupyter notebook with
주피터 노트북에 코드가 너무 많아서 어지럽지 않도록 말이죠
And it contains some messy code to do some data munging, some unraveling of the data to clean it up,
데이터 머깅을 위한 복잡한 코드를 포함하고 있습니다 데이터를 정리하기
I'm going to show you this item, this module now and talk through it.
위한 코드요 이 모듈을 보여드리고 말씀드릴게요
But really there's an exercise for you to go and look through this in more detail and understand it
하지만 비트를 좀 더 자세히 살펴보고 더 자세히 이해하는
a little bit more closely.
연습이 있어요
So as I say it's in its own module items.py and it defines a class item.
말씀드렸듯이 고유한 모듈 항목에 있어요 급이 다른 품목을 정의하죠
And I should point out, before we even get going with it, that we start by setting a constant called
시작하기 전에 짚고 넘어가야 할 것은 get mebodel이라는 상수를 설정하는
base model to be the llama 3.18 billion variant base model.
것부터 시작한다는 점이에요. 180억 가지 변형 기본 모델이죠
Now, you might say to me, what on earth has the llama model got to do with what we're doing at the
라마 모델이 이 작업과 무슨 상관이냐고 하실지도 모르겠네요
moment?
오픈 소스는 다음 주에 공개해요
This week it's all about using frontier models for for fine tuning.
이번 주에는 개척 시대 모델을 미세 조정할 거예요
And here's the answer.
이게 그 답이에요
We're going to be crafting our data set so that it fits within a certain fixed number of tokens as a
정해진 개수의 토큰 안에 들어가도록 데이터 세트를 만들 겁니다 라마 토큰라이저의
maximum tokens for the llama tokenizer.
최대 토큰으로요
And the reason we're going to do that is because that's going to make it cheaper and easier to train
그렇게 하는 이유는 오픈 소스 모델을 사용할 때 더 저렴하고
when we end up using our open source model.
쉽게 훈련할 수 있기 때문이죠
It's also, as I say, going to make it cheaper when we use the frontier model as well, and we want
앞서 말했듯이 개척자 모델을 쓰면 비용이 줄어들 거예요 모두가 같은 조건에서
everyone to be on the same playing field.
작업했으면 좋겠어요
So when we craft our prompts and we fix them to a certain number of tokens, we want to make sure that
프롬프트를 만들고 특정 수의 토큰에 수정할 때 프런티어 모델과 오픈
both the frontier model and the open source model gets the same amount of information.
소스 모델이 같은 양의 정보를 얻도록 해야 해요
If you have more budget and you have ability to train on bigger GPUs, or to use, uh, or more budget
예산이 더 많고 더 큰 GPU로 훈련할 능력이 있거나 프론티어 모델로 예산을 더 쓸 수 있다면
with frontier models, then you can extend the cutoff so that we can have bigger and bigger amounts
컷오프를 연장해서 텍스트를 더 많이 쓸 수 있어요
But I think we've got we're going to you'll see, we'll have plenty of text in each of these data points.
하지만 제 생각엔∙∙∙ 보시면 아시겠지만 각각의 데이터 포인트에 텍스트가 많아요
And so it's perfectly sufficient for our frontier models and our open source models to be training against.
개척 시대 모델과 오픈 소스 모델에 완벽하게 대응할 수 있어요
Anyway, that is why we're looking at the llama model, because we're going to be using its tokenizer
어쨌든 그래서 llama 모델을 살펴보는 겁니다 토큰라이저를
to when we check whether or not we have the right number of characters.
사용할 테니까요 글자의 수가 맞는지 확인하려고요
So the class item, then it is something which each item is going to have a title, a price of course,
클래스 항목은 각각의 항목은 제목을 갖게 되고 가격은 물론 어플라이언스나
a category which will be things like appliances, a token count, how many tokens does it contain.
토큰 개수 같은 카테고리로 구성되죠 토큰은 몇 개인가?
And then most importantly, a prompt which is going to be the text which will be fed into an LLM, which
가장 중요한 건 프롬프트입니다 LLM에 입력될 텍스트죠 훈련하거나
it will then use to either train or to test against.
테스트할 때 사용될 거예요
So just very briefly, the the takeaway is that you must look through this code yourself and satisfy
간단히 말씀드리면, 이 코드를 직접 훑어보시고 스스로 만족하셔야 합니다.
yourself that I'm not doing anything evil and that all of this is just good, uh, wholesome housekeeping
제가 나쁜 짓을 하는 게 아니고 이 모든 게 좋은 일이고, 건전한 가정 환경과, 실밥을 치우는
and cleaning up of strings.
일이라고요.
I have a function called scrub details, which removes stuff from the text that feels like it's going
스크럽 디테일이라는 함수가 있는데 모델이 집중하기 힘들 것 같은 텍스트에서 뭔가를 제거하는
to be distracting to the model.
기능이에요
Stuff like batteries included.
배터리도 포함해서요
Um, and, uh, some other things you see in there, the word manufacturer by manufacturer.
다른 것들도 보이는데 제조업체마다 이름이 있어요
So a bunch of things where it's not relevant or it's not massively relevant, and it seemed better to
관련 없는 게 많거나 크게 관련 없는 게 많죠 소중한 토큰을 다 쓰는
remove it than to have it use up precious tokens by being in there.
것보다 제거하는 게 나을 것 같았어요
There's this, uh, method scrub, which goes through and cleans out weird characters, and it also
메서드 스크럽이 있어요 이상한 캐릭터를 제거하고 여러 공간을 하나로
turns multiple spaces into one space, using some regex for regex ninjas out there.
합치는 거죠 레벡스 닌자를 위한 레벡스 스캐너를 사용해서요
This is probably, uh, easy stuff for you.
당신한텐 쉬운 일이겠죠
For others, this is one of the kinds of bits of script that you can reuse as ways to remove different
다른 분들을 위해 이건 스크립트의 종류 중 하나로 재사용할 수 있습니다 문자열의 다양한 문제를
problems in your in your strings.
제거하는 방법으로요
And you can also test this out at a Jupyter notebook to satisfy yourself that it's doing what it says
주피터 공책으로 시험하면서 틀에 적힌 대로 작동하는지 확인할 수도
on the tin.
있어요
I will mention this line here, because this is just a little extra trick I put in there that is useful
이 라인을 언급할게요 제가 넣은 추가 트릭이거든요 특정 경우에 유용하죠
for our particular case, and it's an example of the kind of thing you only discover when you really
이건 데이터를 깊이 파고들어야만 발견할 수 있는 일종의
dig into the data.
예죠
I noticed that there were a lot of products on Amazon which quote part numbers in their description.
아마존에는 설명서에 숫자를 인용하는 제품이 많더라고요
So they say this is compatible with part number, blah blah and blah.
부품 번호와 호환 가능 어쩌고저쩌고요
And those part numbers are often eight digits, eight characters long or longer and contain letters
그런 부분 번호는 대개 8자리, 8문자 길이 혹은 더 길고 문자와 숫자를 포함하죠
And the problem with that is that when that gets turned into tokens, it uses up a lot of tokens because
여기서 문제는 토큰으로 바뀔 때 토큰을 많이 쓴다는 겁니다 왜냐하면 토큰은
obviously it's not in the vocabulary in any way.
어떤 어휘에도 없기 때문이죠
And so you end up cramming all of your, your token, your unlimited capacity for tokens with tokens
결국 여러분은 토큰을 전부 쑤셔 넣어야 합니다 토큰에 대한 무제한 수용력을 부분 번호를 나타내는
that represent part numbers that are going to be totally irrelevant for our model.
토큰으로 채우는 거죠 우리 모델과는 전혀 상관없는 거예요
So what this line here does is it says if there's any, any word that has eight or more characters and
이 줄의 역할은 8자 이상의 글자가 있고 그 안에 숫자가 있는 단어가 있다면
contains a number inside it, then scrap that word.
그 단어를 삭제하라는 거죠
It's going to be a distraction.
주의를 분산시킬 거예요
Um, so the reason I highlight this is, is really, again, to show that, that you only come across
이걸 강조하는 이유는 다시 말씀드리지만 이런 발견은 데이터를 깊이 파고들어야만
this kind of discovery when you dig into your data.
발견할 수 있어요
You look at lots of examples and you see this happening, and then you come across this.
많은 예시를 보고 이런 일이 일어나는 걸 보고 이걸 발견하게 되죠
You have the moment you try this out.
이걸 시도해볼 기회가 있어요
And when you rerun your model, uh, which you can imagine I've done once or twice in the last few weeks,
모델을 재실행하면 지난 몇 주 동안 한두 번 했던 것 같은데 향상된
you find that you've made an improvement because your data is richer and has more, more accuracy to
걸 발견하게 됩니다 데이터가 더 풍부해지고 정확도도 더 높아졌거든요
So that's an important part of the process.
그게 중요한 과정이에요
And we will then use a method parse, which takes a data point, and then does all of the various scrubbing
그리고 메서드 PARSE를 사용하는데 데이터 포인트를 취하고 다양한 스크래핑과
and stripping and ends up turning it into a prompt.
스트러핑을 해서 프롬프트로 바꾸죠
And along with the prompt, it counts the number of tokens in that prompt.
프롬프트와 함께 그 안의 토큰 개수도 세죠
And you're going to see the prompt in just a second.
잠시 후에 프롬프트를 보실 거예요
But the prompt is the thing that's going to get passed into an LLM, and it will be asked to complete
프롬프트는 LLM으로 전달될 것인데 get을 완료하도록 요청될 거예요
And it's going to say, how much does this cost?
비용은 얼마나 드는지 묻네요
And it's going to have a cost.
비용이 들 거예요
There's going to be an ability to look at a look at a prompt.
프롬프트를 볼 수 있는 기능이 있어요
There's also going to be something called the test prompt, which is the same as the prompt, but it
테스트 프롬프트라는 것도 있어요 프롬프트와 같지만
doesn't reveal the answer.
답을 보여주진 않죠
The prompt will be used during training and it has the answer in there.
훈련 중에 사용될 프롬프트 안에 답이 있어요
So during training, the model will get better and better at predicting the answer during test time.
그래서 훈련을 하다 보면 시험 시간에 답을 예측하는 능력이 점점 더 좋아져요. Get it.
We don't want to show it the answer.
답을 보여드리기 싫어요
We want to give it the text and see whether or not it gets the right answer.
텍스트를 주고 올바른 답이 나오는지 봐야죠
So we have those two different prompts the training prompt and the test prompt.
훈련과 테스트 프롬프트가 두 개 있는데요
Later we're going to talk about breaking down your data into a training set and a test set.
나중에 데이터를 훈련 세트와 테스트 세트로 나누는 걸 얘기할 거예요
You'll see you'll see more.
더 보게 될 거예요
It will become much more clear later on.
나중에 더 명확해질 거예요
So this is the item class.
이게 아이템 클래스죠
And I really suggest that you take more of a look through this.
이걸 좀 더 자세히 보세요
But never fear, we're going to be spending a lot of time with these items and looking at them.
하지만 걱정 마세요 이 물건들을 보면서 많은 시간을 보낼 테니까요
And so you're going to get a good handle for for what this functionality does.
Get it으로 이 기능성 기능에 대한 좋은 정보를 얻을 수 있어요
So back here, what we're now going to do is create one of these items objects for everything in in
이제 여기서 할 것은 이 아이템 객체를 만드는 겁니다 데이터 집합에 있는 모든
the data set that has a price.
것에 대해서요
So let's run that right now.
지금 실행해보죠
So the this is running through that code.
이건 그 코드를 통해 실행되고 있어요
It's it's doing the scrubbing.
문지르는 거예요
It's removing things like part numbers.
파트 넘버 같은 걸 제거하는 거죠
It's replacing weird characters with with with with spaces.
이상한 캐릭터들을 공간으로 대체하는 거죠
And it's creating a prompt and then making sure that the prompt will fit into a decent number of tokens.
프롬프트를 생성해서 여러 개의 토큰에 맞게 하는 것이죠
So all of that is happening right now, and it's going to be doing that for the 40 odd thousand appliances,
현재 모든 게 진행 중이고 4만여 개의 가전제품을 위한 일이 될 거예요
home appliances that have a price.
가격이 붙은 가전제품요
So it should be just about wrapping up now.
이제 마무리할 때가 된 것 같아요
While it's finishing that off I will prepare for us to look at.
다 익는 동안 제가 볼 준비를 할게요
It's done.
다 됐어요
There we go.
됐어요
So let's say let's just have a look at the first first one in there.
첫 번째 것을 보도록 하죠
So the first one in there is a rack roller and stud assembly kit.
첫 번째 키트는 랙 롤러 스터드 조립 키트예요
Full pack by Ami parts replaces blah blah blah blah blah.
아미의 풀 팩이 어쩌고저쩌고 부품을 대체한대요
So this is the the title of the item and that's how much it costs $9.
이게 그 항목의 제목이고 가격은 9달러예요
And you will indeed see that in the title of the item.
그 항목의 제목에서 그걸 볼 수 있어요
There are these part numbers, these long part numbers.
파트 번호가 있어요 긴 파트 번호요
Let's see another one.
다른 것도 보죠
Let's see the first item in there.
첫 번째 항목을 보죠
Again, the first item which is.
첫 번째 항목이죠
A compatible A door pivot block compatible.
호환되는 A 도어 피벗 블록 호환이요
Kenmore KitchenAid.
켄모어 키친에이드요
Maytag whirlpool refrigerator.
메이택 월풀 냉장고예요
Again, lots of part numbers in there.
다시 말하지만 많은 파트 번호가 있어요
So let's now look at what happens if I look at the prompt that that I say that this function created
이제 어떻게 되는지 보죠 이 함수가 생성된 항목을 프롬프트에서 볼게요
Even try that again.
다시 해 봐요
Let's print that.
프린트하죠
So it comes up formatted with nice empty lines.
그래서 멋진 빈 행과 함께 형식이 나타나요
So this is what the prompt says.
프롬프트가 말하는 게 이거예요
How much does this cost to the nearest dollar.
이건 얼마 정도 할까요?
I'll talk more about that to the nearest dollar.
그 얘기는 최대한 많이 할게요
In a later times.
나중에 봐요
We'll talk about why I ended up going with that and and the pros and cons.
왜 그렇게 했는지 장단점이 뭔지 얘기해 보죠
So how much does this cost to the nearest dollar.
이건 얼마 정도 하나요?
And here then is there's actually one line for the, for the, for the heading and one line for the
여기 보면 한 줄은 제목이고 한 줄은 설명이에요
And what you'll see is that, sure enough, these part numbers have been plucked out from this description,
여러분이 보실 것은 이 부분 번호가 이 설명에서 뽑힌 겁니다 잘려진
and you'll see that it has been truncated.
걸 보실 수 있죠
When we've got to the end of a certain number of tokens.
패의 개수가 다 되면요
It's actually, uh, comes to just under 180 tokens, is what I've kept.
제가 보관한 건 180토큰이 조금 안 돼요
And that's what you can see here.
여기서 볼 수 있죠
And you can tell from reading this that it's a rich description of the item itself.
이걸 읽어 보면 그 물건에 대한 풍부한 설명이 나와요
That should be sufficient for training.
훈련에는 충분할 거예요
Let's take a look at the next one.
다음 사진을 보죠
This of course, is our pivot block.
이건 물론 피벗 블록이고요
Our door pivot block.
도어 피벗 블록이에요
Let's go for number 100 and Ice Maker mech.
100번과 제빙기 기계요
This is a Samsung replacement part.
삼성 부품이에요
So you'll also notice there are a lot of things in here that are parts and replacement parts.
여기 보시면 부품과 대체 부품들이 많이 들어 있어요
Again consistent with what we saw before that this space could be crowded out by some of the bits and
아까도 보셨듯이 이 공간은 저렴한 교체 부품
pieces like like replacement parts that are lower cost.
때문에 꽉 차게 될 거예요
Although somewhat surprisingly, this this part is $118, so it's not not such a simple part.
하지만 좀 놀랍게도 이 부분은 118달러예요 그리 간단한 부분이 아니죠
I hope I never need this particular, uh, Samsung Assembly ice maker mech.
이 삼성 조립식 아이스메이커 메크는 필요 없었으면 좋겠어요
Um, okay, so this is looking at the training prompt.
자, 이건 훈련 시간을 보는 건데요
This is what we'll be passing in during training time.
훈련할 때 통과시킬 것들이에요
And so the model will be will be given this and it will start to learn how best to recreate this price
모델에게 이걸 주고 훈련 기간 동안 이 가격을 어떻게 재현할지 배우게
here during training time.
될 거예요
What about during test time.
시험 시간에는요?
What about when it's time to assess whether or not the model is doing any good?
모델이 효과가 있는지 평가할 때는 어떨까요?
So let's look at this guy at item number 100 and see what we will do when it comes to test time.
100번 아이템을 봅시다 테스트 시간에 어떻게 하는지 보죠
We will then.
그러죠
Provide the model with this.
이걸 모델로 제공하세요
It's exactly the same but it ends here.
똑같은데 여기서 끝나죠
And of course the idea is that the model will have seen so many examples of this, covering such a wide
물론 그 아이디어는 모델은 이것의 정말 많은 예들을 봤을 거라는 거죠 정말 다양한
variety of different items that when it's shown this again at runtime, it will know how to complete
다양한 항목을 다루고 런타임에 이걸 다시 보여드릴 때 어떻게 완료하는지 알
it will it will have a good nuanced understanding based on this description that will help it to complete
겁니다 이 설명을 기반으로 미묘한 이해를 잘해서 이 가격을 완료하도록
this price.
돕겠죠
All right.
좋아요
Let's look at how many tokens we typically have in these items by doing another of our diagrams.
이 아이템들에 토큰이 얼마나 많은지 봅시다 다른 다이어그램을 이용해서요
And what you'll see is that the highest number of tokens is 178.
가장 많은 패가 178개인 걸 알 수 있어요
Never quite get to 180, and the average is 176.
180까지 못 올라가고 평균 176까지 가죠 Get it
It's really sort of crammed in there.
정말 꽉 들어찼어요
So we've generally generally selected and and crafted data sets that have about this much information.
그래서 일반적으로 이 정도 양의 정보를 가진 데이터 세트를 선택하고 다듬었어요
And it comes to up to 180 tokens.
180냥까지 나올 거예요
And as I say, this is going to be very helpful during training because we're going to know the maximum
훈련할 때 큰 도움이 될 것입니다 아이템을 지원하는
number of tokens we need to be able to support in any item, and it's also going to keep costs lower
데 필요한 최대 토큰의 수를 알 수 있고 프론티어 모델을 사용할 때 비용을 절감할
when we end up using frontier models for this.
수 있기 때문이죠
Okay.
네
And then let's just have another look at the distribution of prices in these items that we have selected.
그런 다음 우리가 선택한 이 아이템의 가격 분배를 다시 한 번 보죠
Here we go.
시작할게요
So the average price is $100.
평균 가격이 100달러예요
Uh, over here the highest price is, uh, almost $11,000.
최고 11,000달러까지 받을 수 있어요
So in the process of doing some weeding out, we have actually removed that super expensive microwave
잡초를 제거하는 과정에서 엄청나게 비싼 전자레인지를 제거했어요
But we've still got something that's fairly expensive.
하지만 여전히 꽤 비싼 걸 사야 해요
You can figure out what that is by by by replicating what I had above.
제가 위에 쓴 걸 복제하면 그게 뭔지 알 수 있어요
Um, and you can still see that the distribution is very heavily skewed towards super cheap things that
지금도 보시다시피 아주 저렴한 물건 쪽으로 유통되고 있어요 우리가 본
are presumably replacement parts, as we have been seeing.
것처럼 부품을 대체하는 거죠
So that is another area for us to investigate next time.
다음에 조사할 또 다른 지역이네요
Uh, and so I did want to mention something that that visualizing these data sets is something we'll
이 데이터 집합을 시각화하는 건 앞으로 자주 하게 될
be doing a lot.
거예요
And you will be doing a lot in different ways.
다양한 방식으로 많은 걸 하게 될 거예요
Uh, it's it's nice to be able to take advantage of various features in matplotlib.
맷플로틀리브의 다양한 기능을 활용할 수 있어서 좋아요
And one of them is that it allows you to produce charts with many a huge array of different colors.
그중 하나는 다양한 색상의 차트를 만들 수 있다는 거죠
And if you would like to know what those colors are, I've included a link that will take you to the
그 색들이 뭔지 알고 싶으시면 Mattplotlib 페이지로
page, uh, in matplotlib, where it will describe the different color schemes that you can use, including,
연결되는 링크를 달아 두었습니다 사용할 수 있는 다양한 색 배열을 설명하고 있습니다 xkcd
uh, something called xkcd's colors.
색상도 포함해서요
And it's good to take a look at that.
그걸 살펴보는 건 좋은 일이죠
Uh, so this is, uh, just a by the by as a little extra thing for you to bookmark.
이건 책갈피로 남기기 좋은 작은 단서예요
Uh, another another little pro tip for today, but the real to do's, what you have to do now, please,
오늘 팁을 하나 더 드리자면 지금 하셔야 할 일은 아이템 클래스를
is go and look at the item class.
보시는 거예요
I realize I went through it quickly.
제가 너무 빨리 지나갔어요
It's because it's got some of the more gruesome data A scrubbing the data munging that one does based
데이터 머징 스크러빙이 좀 더 섬뜩하기 때문이죠 실제 데이터 예제에 근거해 데이터를
on real examples of data to make the data as high quality as possible.
최대한 고품질로 만드는 거예요
And I haven't bored you with all of the details, but that's partly because I trust that you will now
제가 너무 자세히 설명해서 지루하지 않으셨다면 이제 직접 들어가서 자세히 보시리라
go in and look at the details yourself.
믿었기 때문일 거예요
Use JupyterLab to to investigate, try out and understand how these functions have cleaned up some of
JupyterLab을 이용해 이런 기능이 어떻게 데이터를 정화했는지 조사하고 이해하세요
the data and got us to a point where we have about 180 tokens of rich description, rich wording for
덕분에 약 180개의 토큰이 생겼습니다 각 데이터 포인트에 대한 풍부한 설명과
each of our data points, each of our items that will be used as training prompts and test prompts in
단어들이죠 각각의 항목은 미래에 훈련과 테스트 프롬프트로 사용될 거예요
So next time we'll be expanding this to combine many, many other types of products.
다음에는 더 많은 제품을 결합하도록 확장할 거예요
And if you thought this data set was a large data set, you ain't seen nothing yet.
이 데이터 모음이 크다고 생각했다면 아직 아무것도 못 본 거예요
So prepare for that.
그러니 준비하세요
But first, a couple more slides to wrap up this day.
하지만 먼저 슬라이드 몇 개만 더 보고 마무리하죠